Guide to the Hadassah, Pittsburgh Chapter, Records 1917-1968 AIS.1968.13
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hadassah Records
1917-1968
1940-1968
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Hadassah, the Women's Zionist Organization of America. Pittsburgh Chapter
AIS.1968.13
1.25 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
Hadassah, founded in 1912 by Henrietta Szold, is a volunteer Jewish women's community organization whose purpose is to promote Zionist Jewish institutions and enterprises in Israel and to foster Zionist ideals in the United States. Materials in the collection span 1917-1968 and include announcements, ballots, brochures, clippings, constitution, correspondence, invitations, membership cards, memorabilia, newsletters, pamphlets, programs, (annual and biennial) reports, yearbooks and a play and song.
History
Hadassah, the Women's Zionist Organization of America, was founded in 1912 by Henrietta Szold and is a volunteer women's organization whose members are motivated and inspired to strengthen their partnership with Israel, ensure Jewish continuity and realize their potential as a dynamic force in American society. In Israel, Hadassah initiates and supports health care, education and youth institutions, and land development. In the United States, Hadassah enhances the quality of American and Jewish life through its education and youth programs, promotes health awareness and provides personal enrichment and growth for its members.
Scope and Content Notes
Materials include announcements, ballots, brochures, clippings, constitution, correspondence, invitations, membership cards, memorabilia, newsletters, pamphlets, programs, (annual and biennial) reports, yearbooks and a play and song. The bulk of the materials span 1940-1968. Series I and II relate to the Pittsburgh and National Chapters respectively and Series III contains additional information on the Pittsburgh Chapter.
Series I and II contain the constitution, annual and biennial reports, the National Chapter song, Hadassah, Daughters of Zion, information regarding Donor Luncheon Programs and national conventions, yearbooks, Pittsburgh Hadassah News and the Pittsburgh Chapter of Hadassah, Monthly Bulletin.
Series III contains Donor Luncheon Books, yearbooks and The Pittsburgh Story and Shoppers' Guide.
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Hadassah, Pittsburgh Chapter on August 14, 1968.
Previous Citation
Hadassah, Pittsburgh Chapter Records, 1917-1968, AIS.1968.13, Archives Service Center, University of Pittsburgh
Hadassah, Pittsburgh Chapter, Records, 1917-1968, Archives of Industrial Society, University Library System, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, PA 15260
Women; Ethnic groups; Social action; Societies; Women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Jewish women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Jews -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh -- Societies and clubs; Clubs -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Hadassah, the Women's Zionist Organization of America. Pittsburgh Chapter
- Pittsburgh Chapter, I.
  - Standard Constitution for Local Chapters, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1917-1965 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ballots, 1943-1945 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Membership Cards, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Donor Luncheon Programs, 1940-1946 (intermittent) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Freedom Donor Luncheon Program, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - National Conventions, 1921, 1935, 1941, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - East and West (A Symbolic Play with Music), Syria Mosque, program, December 15, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Invitations and Announcements, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper Clippings, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous Memorabilia, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Yearbooks, 1929-1932, 1934-1936, 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Pittsburgh Hadassah News, (vol. 22-35), 1955-1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Pittsburgh Chapter of Hadassah, Monthly Bulletin,(vol. 1-7), 1933-1940 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Pittsburgh Hadassah News, Special Editions, 1955-1957, 1959, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- National Chapter, II.
  - Hadassah, Daughters of Zion, lyrics by Mrs. Herman Hollander, music by Alex Podnos (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Hadassah Newsletter,Convention Issue 1958, vol. 38, no.8, November 1941 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brochures and pamphlets, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Additional Information on the Pittsburgh Chapter, III.
  - Donor Luncheon Books, 1950, 1952-1965, 1967-1968 (Box 2, Volume 1-17)
  - Yearbooks, 1941-1949 (Box 2, Volume 1-8)
  - The Pittsburgh Story and Shoppers' Guide, 1947-1948 (Box 2, Volume 1)